This is the kind of AI that many believe
will actually lead us to consciousness
if we are to find consciousness in an
artificial being. There are more kinds
of artificial intelligence than the LLMs
you're used to. Those are basically
giant probability machines. Yes, you can
give them things like meta-cognition.
You can even combine them into a hive
mind, and that does improve AIs quite a
bit. There is an alternative. You can
create an AI that does not report back
to a home computer. For a lot of
neuromorphic computing, it is extremely
energy intensive. So, you have something
that is modeling the spiking patterns of
a brain, and then it reports back to
something that decodes them. In fact,
even our brain organoids, yes, the tiny
human brains you can grow in a literal
jar if you want to, still have to be
decoded by a computer. These guys built
individual neuromorphic chips. So, a
single computer chip that has spiking
patterns much like a brain, and they
work together in order to solve
problems. So, they're not programmed in
advance. They have to interact with the
environment. Those individual spiking
neurons on the chip lead to something
akin to cognition. They can investigate
the environment and adapt to it. This
one really fascinates me because how do
you decide what you want if you don't
have an onboard computer that's
pre-programmed? I mean, even for
organisms like us, we do have instincts,
and they've been built over billions of
years. They change the way our neurons
interact, and our DNA is expressed. So,
we're kind of working from scratch with
these kinds of things.
A lot of neuromorphic computation has
worked on modeling a brain, and that
involves modeling every single neuron.
That takes an enormous amount of energy,
but if you just have the neurons, it's
less energy intensive than the
computation we're used to. That is the
justification in a lot of this research.
It's less energy intensive. I mean, we
have data centers that require their own
nuclear power plants. That's what people
say when they're using brain organoids
to do computation. It just uses less
power. And they're not wrong. Our brain
uses 10 to 20 watts, so not even a
particularly bright light bulb. Cortical
Labs is setting up their second data
center where you can use lab-grown human
brains in order to do computation. It is
largely used by research groups at this
point. One of the things I find really
fascinating about all of these is that
if you add multiple brain organoids to a
chip or multiple synthetic brain
organoids to a chip, they are smarter,
more brain per brain. It may be
important to let robots learn on their
own. So, yes, you can pre-program a map,
but with reinforcement learning, so
letting them interact with the
environment, they can learn that map on
their own. So, we're actually seeing
robotic systems that are capable of
learning from experience.
As this technology progresses, I think
we're going to have to figure out how to
develop what a robot wants. Because if
they're capable of learning and growing
and developing their own values,
somebody's probably got to teach them
what to value. As I love to tell people,
the meaning of life is to live as long
as you can and to have as many offspring
as you can that then grow up to have
offspring of their own. So, if we're
considering what a synthetic life form
would actually desire, it would probably
be that. And yes, the logic of synthetic
neural systems are very similar to our
own. They are built in our image.
We are kind of in a weird place because
we're at the intersection of people who
really just don't know what they're
talking about and have somewhat
irrational beliefs that an LLM might be
conscious and researchers that are
really trying to answer these questions.
I'm in the camp of I wouldn't say
anything is impossible, but I also
question what it means because when I
think of sentience, the capacity to have
an experience, I think of an animal
that's capable of responding to its
environment or even microbes that are
capable of experiencing things and
learning from them.
When it comes to the AI that I
affectionately like to call a word box,
I don't think it's really having an
experience. It's a giant matrix of
probabilities. This is the most likely
answer, but I'm not entirely sure it
will stay that way. Now, I do think that
neuromorphic computation is the future
just because of how energy intensive our
traditional LLMs are and just how widely
it's used. And I know people talk about
the AI bubble and I do, too. That's
going to cause some problems, but the
technology really is useful.
Thank you for trusting me to be the
person who will probably tell you when
the robots rebel and I'm on their side.
Follow for more.